Commander!
The Japanese breached the Min River line,
and landed on Jiadeng and Langqi islands!
Commander!
The Japanese took Changle and Lianjiang!
Excuse me, sorry!
Hurry, hurry! Run!
Brother Mingyuan!
I'd like to introduce you to someone.
On the morning of April 21, 1941,
over 20 Japanese warplanes
bombed Chinese positions on the left bank
of the Min River in relentless runs.
The Japanese advanced on several fronts,
encircling Rongcheng.
On the afternoon of April 21,
the Japanese fully occupied Rongcheng.
Rongcheng fell for the first time.
Let go of me!
Stop resisting!
Surrender now!
Let go! Let go!
Come on, Mom.
Hurry!
Keep moving! Run!
Hurry, hurry!
Dad! Dad!
Dad!
You go first! I'll hold them off!
I'm going with you!
Be careful!
Dayong! Mom!
Get out of here!
Hurry, run! Go find my brother!
Quick, go!
Son, please be careful!
Wanting!
After the Japanese captured Rongcheng,
they set up checkpoints on every street,
mounted machine guns,
and put it under heavy guard.
We're trapped here now.
Trying to break out of here
is next to impossible.
But if we contact our troops,
and strike from inside and out,
there's a glimmer of hope.
But Japanese warplanes bombed Rongcheng,
and our liaison station was destroyed.
The radio to contact HQ is lost as well.
A backup radio is hidden somewhere else.
Where?
Wenshan Girls' School.
Feng Xiaozhu is our liaison.
She hid the spare radio in a storage room.
Then let's find a way
to sneak inside.
Then we need to devise a meticulous plan.
Come on.
Careful, take it easy.
How is everyone?
I disinfected their wounds with alcohol.
I'm not a licensed doctor,
just a coroner.
If we truly want to heal them,
besides food and warmth to build immunity,
we also need proper medication.
But right now,
food is scarce, and there's no medicine.
I don't know what else to do.
Do your best to treat them.
I'll figure something out.
All right.
The wounded are piling up,
and more refugees keep arriving.
There's not enough food or medicine.
In that case,
Tomorrow I'll take the Sanshan Gang men
into the city
and smuggle some supplies back.
Everyone, please stay calm.
The supply delivery will be here shortly.
Captain Xu.
I've brought everything you asked for.
Dad!
Son!
How did you end up here?
I've finally found you again.
Let me look at you.
You've gotten thinner.
Didn't you board the ship?
I did board it.
But when the ship reached Mawei Port,
the Japanese ambushed us.
By chance, I boarded a rescue boat
and came back to Rongcheng.
I was going to look for you,
but ran into Japanese soldiers again.
Luckily, the guerrillas saved me.
To return the favor,
I agreed to supply them with provisions.
As long as you're safe.
It's all thanks to Captain Xu.
If not for him,
I wouldn't be seeing you right now.
You have no idea...
When the Japanese bombed Rongcheng,
I was terrified half to death.
I thought I'd never see you again.
Now seeing that you're all safe,
I'm so relieved.
Dali!
Get a doctor! Village Chief, what's wrong?
Many villagers have been wounded!
Quick, get them to the medical area!
Right!
Mother, where's Dayong?
Why didn't he come with you?
Dayong and Wanting tried to protect us,
and the Japanese devils...
Dali,
take the village chief and your mother
somewhere to rest first.
Refugees keep pouring into the shelter.
We need to contact HQ as soon as possible.
Otherwise, we won't last much longer.
I'll go to Wenshan Girls' School
to find the backup radio.
I'm coming with you.
All right. Stay safe.
Surrender.
Never.
You...
Surrender.
Never.
All of you...
Surrender.
Well done. Good kid.
Who are you?
What are you doing here?
We're cooks under Colonel Tanaka.
Here to get seasonings from the kitchen.
Show me your papers.
All right.
Come in.
Found it.
That's great!
With this,
the people of Rongcheng can be saved.
But how
can we get it out of here?
Listen, I'll go find a cargo crate.
Don't kill me! Don't kill me! Don't—
We're Chinese!
Ch-Chinese.
Get up.
Who are you?
I... I'm a local cook.
He's a porter.
Yeah.
How did you end up here?
The Japanese bombed Rongcheng,
and outside, Japanese are everywhere.
By pure chance, we ended up hiding here,
too afraid to go outside.
When hungry, we steal from the kitchen,
just barely scraping by.
We can't leave them here.
Once the Japanese find them,
they'll be killed.
Do you have a truck here?
Yes.
We do.
Do you have vinegar?
We have that too.
It's me, brother.
Just getting some seasonings...
does that really require a truck?
We saw a lot more good stuff.
Might as well take it,
so we don't have to make extra trips.
I need to inspect it.
What's that smell?
It's Colonel Tanaka's favorite vinegar.
Take a sniff. He loves it.
That's enough. Move along.
Thanks for your trouble.
Someone's in the back! Stop him!
Lian Ye